Finding Aid for American Legion Auxiliary, Department of Michigan records, 1917-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
American Legion Auxiliary, Department of Michigan records
1917-2008
1933-2005
American Legion Auxiliary. Department of Michigan.
2008148 Br 2
Sister organization to the American Legion organization for Michigan veterans. The record group documents the Department’s administrative functions, its publications, and involvement with the Girls State government simulation program.
25 linear feet in 26 boxes
7 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by the American Legion Auxiliary, Department of Michigan (Donor no. 10085 ) in February 2008.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
Women who had relatives in the 126th Infantry 32nd Division had organized themselves in 1917 after the Grand Rapids Michigan National Guard had left to contribute to the war effort. Two years later, the American Legion Auxiliary, Department of Michigan was officially created as a Unit to the Carl A. Johnson Post Number Two on July 9, 1919 (the American Legion itself was organized at the close of World War One, prompting a request to assimilate into the official structure of the veterans organization).
The Auxiliary not only supports members of the American Legion, it is also a major source of volunteers working on behalf of veterans residing in Veterans Administration hospitals. Auxiliary members also contribute a great deal of time, effort and money to programs to help veterans, their community and especially children.1
The Department of Michigan began holding state annual conventions in 1921 to facilitate the administrative functions of the Auxiliary, documenting not only these conventions but the Executive Committee meetings as well. They also sponsor many programs, most of which are highlighted during particular months. Some of these programs include: Americanism, Girls State/Nation, Cavalcade of Memories, National Security, and Poppy Days.
The record group of the American Legion Auxiliary, Department of Michigan documents the organization's annual meetings, history, fundraising, and affiliation with the Girls State program. The series are: Administrative Files, Publications, Historical Materials, Girls State, Topical, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
American Legion. Auxiliary. Dept. of Michigan.; American Legion. Dept. of Michigan.; Michigan Girls State.; Veterans--Michigan--Societies, etc.; Women--Societies and clubs--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Administrative Files, 1921-2003
  The Administrative Files (18.5 linear feet) has a heavy emphasis on documenting the annual conventions, executive committee meetings, and the activities of organization presidents. Other administrative functions are documented as well. Note: while most of the years have their own folders or dividers, some have been left in binders with the year clearly visible and were not placed in folders.
  - Annual Conventions and Executive Committee Meetings, 1921-1997
    (chronological by year; includes minutes of the meetings)
    - 1921-1945 (Box 1)
    - 1946-1951 (Box 2)
    - 1952-1955 (Box 3)
    - 1956-1959 (Box 4)
    - 1960-1962 (Box 5)
    - 1963-1967 (Box 6)
    - 1968-1972 (Box 7)
    - 1973-1976 (Box 8)
    - 1977-1980 (Box 9)
    - 1981-1984 (Box 10)
    - 1985-1988 (Box 11)
    - 1989-1992 (Box 12)
    - 1993-1997 (Box 13)
    - "State and National Conventions, 1931-1932" (Volume 1)
  - Annual Reports
    (chronological by year, missing years 1962-1963, 1965, 1999, 2003-2005)
    - 1928-1993, 4 folders (Box 14)
    - 1994-2008 (Box 15)
  - Constitution and By-Laws, 1927-1987 (Box 15)
    (not a complete run)
  - Committee Appointments, 2000-2004 (Box 15)
  - Department Officers, 1955-1992; 5 folders (Box 15)
  - Guides
    - Unit Handbook, 1947-1985 (Box 15)
    - General, 1948-1993 (Box 15)
  - President Biographies
    - Viola Starkey, 1955-1956 (Box 16)
    - Grace Johnston, 1959-1960 (Box 16)
    - Edna Schuitema, 1960-1961 (Box 16)
    - Jane Schultz, 1967-1968 (Box 16)
    - Margaret Rohrer, 1968-1969 (Box 16)
    - Romaine Roethel, 1969-1970 (Box 16)
    - Dorothy Finkbeiner, 1971-1972 (Box 16)
    - Dorothy Volkers, 1972-1973 (Box 16)
    - Helen Hodges, 1973-1974 (Box 16)
    - Louise Ferguson, 1975-1976 (Box 16)
    - Marylyn Winteringham, 1976-1977 (Box 16)
    - Imogene Cowgill, 1977-1978 (Box 16)
    - Loretta Fisher, 1978-1979 (Box 16)
    - Donna Baley, 1979-1980 (Box 16)
    - Betty Cline, 1980-1981 (Box 16)
    - Catherine Casey, 1981-1982 (Box 16)
    - Melissa McNee, 1982-1983 (Box 16)
    - Virginia Lefevre, 1984-1985 (Box 16)
    - Phyllis Van Hill, 1985-1986 (Box 16)
    - Helen Currie, 1986-1987 (Box 16)
    - Corinne Lovelock, 1987-1988 (Box 16)
    - Mary Jane Choate, 1988-1989 (Box 16)
    - Lauretta Riddle, 1989-1990 (Box 16)
    - Grace Veldman, 1990-1991 (Box 16)
    - Marilyn Popp, 1991-1992 (Box 16)
    - Patricia Jewell, 1992-1993 (Box 16)
    - Dorothy Mae Stewart, 1993-1994 (Box 16)
    - Ivy Reinhardt, 1996-1997 (Box 16)
    - Donna Fuelling, 1997-1998 (Box 16)
    - Jacklyn Skinner, 1998-1999 (Box 16)
    - Marian "Pic" Webster, 1999-2000 (Box 16)
    - Dorothy Huges, undated (Box 16)
    - Frances Crakes, undated (Box 16)
    - Catherine Bogart, undated (Box 16)
  - National Officer Biographies, 1977-1994 (Box 16)
  - Membership Tally Sheets, 1998-2001 (Box 16)
  - Unit Handbooks, 1970-1978 (Box 16)
  - Financial Materials, 1973-1980; 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Resolutions and Memos, 1996 (Box 17)
  - Special Memos, 1983-1984 (Box 17)
  - Application for Unit Charters, 1920; 1932; 1958 (Box 17)
  - Canceled Charter Correspondence, 1995-2001 (Box 17)
  - General
    - 2000-2001, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - 2001-2002 (Box 18)
    - 2002-2003 (Box 18)
  - Charters, 1937 (Folder 1)
- Publications, 1827-2005
  The Publications (1 linear feet) series contains a runs of the Auxiliary News and the American Legion Auxiliary (both were Bulletins); several programs for the annual conventions are also included.
  - American Legion Auxiliary, 1932-1951; 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Auxiliary News
    (includes bulletins)
    - 1938-1948, 1 folders (Box 19)
  - Programs of annual convention, 1927-1972; 2000-2005; 7 folders (Box 19)
- Historical Materials
  The annual histories of the department make up the bulk of the Historical Materials (2.5 linear feet) series. Also, the Department's anniversaries and clippings from the 1930s provide additional material.
  - Anniversaries
    - 50th (Box 20)
      (includes 2 scrapbooks)
    - "50 Years" (Volume 2)
    - "50th Anniversary" (Volume 3)
    - 75th and 100th (Box 20)
  - Past Presidents, 2 folders (Box 21)
    (includes photographs)
  - "Past National President: Mrs. Norton H. Pearl ", 1946-1947 (Volume 4)
  - Histories, 1917-2004; 26 folders (Box 21)
    (not a complete run; includes photographs)
  - Clippings
    - 1933-1934, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - 1938-1939, 3 folders (Box 22)
- Girls State
  Girls State (1.5 linear feet) is a government simulation program comprised of approximately 400 female students from around the state. The objective is to provide "hands on" training in city, county, and state government. Citizens of Girls State participate in a variety of activities. All branches of government (executive, legislative and judicial) are explored. The series contains government manuals, yearbooks, and scrapbooks documenting the various functions of this program.
  - Government Manuals, 1987; 1996 (Box 22)
  - Yearbooks, 1974-2004; 2 folders (Box 22)
    (missing 2002-2003)
  - Minutes of Board Meetings, 1941-1959; 2 volumes (Box 22)
  - Legislation, 1990 (Box 22)
    (Girls State Day Proclamation and Resolution Commemorating 50th Anniversary)
  - Girls Nation, 1974; 1976 (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous, 1961-1977 (Box 22)
  - General Administration
    - 2001 (Box 23)
    - 2002 (Box 23)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1941 (Volume 5)
    - 1943-1944 (Volume 6)
    - Undated (Volume 7)
- Topical Files
  The Topical (1 linear foot) series documents various small-scale initiatives and programs; two scrapbooks are also included.
  - Banquet Programs, 1970 (Box 24)
  - Children's Billet, 1923 (Box 24)
  - Emblem and Pin Sales, 1979-1983 (Box 24)
  - Hodges, Helen Correspondence, 1984 (Box 24)
  - Membership Cards, 1922-1956 (Box 24)
  - Memorial Services, 1969-1970 (Box 24)
  - Michigan Veterans' Facility, 1981 (Box 24)
  - Third Zone (Box 24)
  - FIDAC Auxiliary (Interallied Federation of Ex-Service Men), 1933-1935 (Box 24)
    (a scrapbook with some items in French and Italian)
  - "Scrapbook,", 1955-1956 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 24)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials (1.5 linear feet) series contains photographs, a videocassette, and a slide show documenting their poppy days (a fundraising activity).
  - "The Fight Against Blindness", VHS tape (Box 25)
  - Photographs
    - "The Poppy Story", slide show (Box 25)
    - Individuals (Box 26)
    - Group Shots, 2 folders (Box 26)